<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!-- name="GENERATOR" content="github.com/mmarkdown/mmark Mmark Markdown Processor - mmark.miek.nl" -->
<rfc version="3" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-brotman-ietf-bimi-guidance-12" submissionType="IETF" category="bcp" xml:lang="en" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" consensus="true">

<front>
<title abbrev="BIMI-GG">General Guidance for Implementing Branded Indicators for Message Identification (BIMI)</title><seriesInfo value="draft-brotman-ietf-bimi-guidance-12" stream="IETF" status="bcp" name="RFC"></seriesInfo>
<author initials="A." surname="Brotman" fullname="Alex Brotman"><organization>Comcast</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>alex_brotman@comcast.com</email>
</address></author>
<author initials="T." surname="Zink" fullname="Terry Zink"><organization>Zink Magical Contraptions</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>tzink@terryzink.com</email>
</address></author>
<author initials="M." surname="Bradshaw" fullname="Marc Bradshaw"><organization>Fastmail</organization><address><postal><street></street>
</postal><email>marc@fastmailteam.com</email>
</address></author>
<date year="2025" month="May" day="1"></date>
<area>Applications</area>
<workgroup></workgroup>

<abstract>
<t>This document is meant to provide guidance to various entities so
that they may implement Brand Indicators for Message Identification
(BIMI).  This document is a companion to various other BIMI drafts,
which should first be consulted.</t>
</abstract>

</front>

<middle>

<section anchor="introduction"><name>Introduction</name>
<t>The Brand Indicators for Message Identification (BIMI) specification
introduces a method by which Mail User Agent (MUA, e.g., an email client)
providers combine DMARC-based message authentication with cryptographic
methods to ensure the identity of a sender. If the identity is ensured,
the MUA can then retrieve sender-selected iconography to display within
the MUA. This displayed iconography grants the sender brand impressions
via the BIMI-capable MUA, and should be a driving factor for the adoption
of authenticated email.</t>

<section anchor="terminology"><name>Terminology</name>
<t>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, &quot;SHOULD&quot;,
&quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;NOT RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and &quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this
document are to be interpreted as described in [BCP 14] <xref target="RFC2119"></xref>
<xref target="RFC8174"></xref> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="goals-for-bimi"><name>Goals for BIMI</name>
<t>As stated in other BIMI drafts, BIMI intends to advance email authentication
by granting a sending party brand impressions as long as the message
passes authentication mechanisms and meets other receiver qualifications
(reputation, encryption, allow listing, et cetera). DMARC currently has wide
adoption by some of the Internet's larger brands, but there is still a long
tail of small-to-medium size brands (and many large ones) that do not have it.
Furthermore, many domains are not employing DMARC enforcement via quarantine
or reject policy, which may allow domain impersonation to continue.
Because BIMI provides a visual presence in the inbox, and because visual
impressions are desirable for brands, BIMI provides an incentive for marketers
to spur DMARC adoption, whereas a concern purely from security may not.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="who-should-implement-bimi"><name>Who should implement BIMI?</name>

<section anchor="brands"><name>Brands</name>
<t>Organizations take great care to create and promote the image associated with their
brand.  By implementing BIMI, and creating additional impressions, an organization
can foster a stronger tie with customers.  In exchange for positive
authentication, and strong DMARC policies, the MBP and MUA may show the associated
logos with those messages.  It should be noted that the domain holder must
implement those strong policy on not just a sub-domain, but also the Organizational
Domain.</t>
<t>As a Brand holder, you may need to satisfy these requirements:</t>

<ul>
<li>Ability to alter DNS to host a new TXT record</li>
<li>A web server to host one or two files, depending on your implementation</li>
<li>If you choose to obtain an evidence document, you will need a person to act as
a representative for your company</li>
<li>The desire to have DMARC enforcement (quarantine/reject) policies on both the
organizational and sub-domains. (ex., example.com and sub.example.com)</li>
<li>In the DMARC record, pct must be absent or 100%</li>
</ul>
<t>However, also note that BIMI may not be for every domain. For example, it seems
unlikely that a domain would want to implement BIMI for person-to-person
correspondence. Or if a domain is not meant to send email, the domain holder may
want to explicitly ensure the domain is exempted from BIMI via the BIMI DNS record.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="receiver"><name>Receiver</name>
<t>If your site satisfies the <eref target="#bimi-site-requirements">requirements</eref>, this is likely a &quot;yes&quot;.</t>
<t>As email has evolved over the past three decades, it is no longer a medium of
merely exchanging text, but of enabling people to build rich experiences on top
of it. BIMI provides an incentive for brands to send email more securely
because the desired behavior - a visual imprint in the inbox - first requires
DMARC adoption.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="mua-authors"><name>MUA Authors</name>
<t>The Mail User Agent (MUA) is ultimately responsible for displaying BIMI logos.  This could
be an in-house/proprietary MUA, or something more generally available.  While the MUA may
enable the display of the logos, the responsibility for validating inbound messages lies
with the Receiver/MBP.  MUA Authors should also allow users the option to disable BIMI
logo display.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="mta-authors"><name>MTA Authors</name>
<t>The receiving MTA at the destination is the system that is best suited to evaluate message
authentication, as well as the DMARC and BIMI policies.  The MTA would also be responsible
for creating the additional headers that the MUA is meant to utilize.  In an ideal world,
all MTAs would support BIMI and allow the individual MBPs on deploying BIMI. The MTA would
also ideally allow the MBP to alternately utilize a proxy instead of the direct URL
retrieved from the BIMI record or evidence document.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="terminology-1"><name>Terminology</name>
<t>The following terms are used throughout this document.</t>

<ul>
<li>MTA</li>
<li>MUA</li>
<li>DKIM</li>
<li>SPF</li>
<li>DMARC</li>
<li>MBP</li>
<li>Alignment</li>
<li>Verified Mark Certificate (VMC)</li>
<li>Recipient Domain</li>
<li>Sending Domain</li>
<li>MVA</li>
<li>Local-part</li>
</ul>
<t>For definitions of these terms, see the Appendix.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="receivers"><name>Receivers</name>

<section anchor="site-implementations"><name>Site implementations</name>
<t>In order for a site to correctly implement BIMI, the receiver must be able
to perform the following:</t>

<ul>
<li>Validate SPF</li>
<li>Validate DKIM signatures</li>
<li>Validate DMARC</li>
<li>Discover and fetch a BIMI assertion record using DNS</li>
<li>Fetch a SVG using HTTPS</li>
<li>Validate a SVG using a profile</li>
<li>Add Authentication-Results and BIMI-* Headers to a message</li>
</ul>
<t>Optionally, for a site to correctly implement BIMI evidence document (VMC is one
example) verification, the receiver must be able to perform the following:</t>

<ul>
<li>Fetch the document using HTTPS</li>
<li>Validate the evidence document</li>
<li>Extract a SVG from the evidence document</li>
</ul>
<t>A site may wish to implement URI alteration and image caching for hosted recipients.
By implementing BIMI, a site agrees that through some combination of trust mechanisms,
it will instruct a BIMI-capable MUA to display the image fetched from a URI within the
message headers. This URI is created after the MTA authenticates a message, and is also
(optionally) able to authenticate the evidence document associated with the sending domain.
Discussion of these trust mechanisms is beyond the scope of this document.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="validation-of-a-bimi-message"><name>Validation of a BIMI message</name>

<section anchor="bimi-processing-requirements"><name>BIMI processing requirements</name>
<t>In the BIMI specification, a message MUST be authenticated via DMARC. As stated
in the DMARC draft, this requires that only one of DKIM or SPF must successfully
pass validation with alignment with the organizational domain in the From: address.
However, for additional local security measures, a receiving site may
choose to create additional requirements for senders in order to verify BIMI  (that is,
indicate to a downstream MUA that it is safe to load a BIMI logo in the email client)</t>
<t>This may include, but is not limited to:</t>

<ul>
<li>Requiring both DKIM and SPF to validate and align with the organizational domain
in the From: address (whereas DMARC only requires one of SPF or DKIM to align with
the From: domain).  See below for some Security Concerns.</li>
<li>SPF &quot;strength&quot; requirements (e.g., requiring &quot;-all&quot;, disallowing usage of &quot;?all&quot;
or not allowing inclusion of overly large address spaces)</li>
<li>SMTP delivery via TLS</li>
<li>Feedback Loop registration or other method of registration with the receiving site</li>
<li>Domain reputation via a DNS allow list or other reputation system</li>
</ul>
<t>These localized requirements are at the discretion of the receiving site. In general,
the stricter the criteria, the less chance there is of an MUA erroneously showing a
logo and giving the wrong signal to a user.</t>
<t>Upon receipt of an email, a receiver that implements BIMI should remove or rename any
previously existing BIMI-* headers other than BIMI-Selector, as they may have come
from an attacker (as long as the BIMI-Selector is covered by the DKIM signature; if
not, it should be removed, renamed, or ignored).</t>
<t>Additionally:</t>

<ul>
<li>It may be useful to have messages exiting a site to have those BIMI-* headers removed
as well.</li>
<li>It is useful for a site that has not implemented BIMI to remove those headers so
that an MUA that does make use of those headers would not accidentally display a BIMI
image when the message has not been properly authenticated by the email receiver (even
though an MUA should not make use of BIMI headers and instead rely upon settings from
the mail store, it is possible that some MUAs will nevertheless use headers
without taking appropriate precautions).</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="verified-mark-certificate-vmc-validation"><name>Verified Mark Certificate (VMC) Validation</name>
<t>(Currently, see document in Reference below)</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="communicating-bimi-results-between-the-mta-and-the-mua"><name>Communicating BIMI results between the MTA and the MUA</name>
<t>In order for a receiver that has implemented BIMI to notify an MUA that it should
display the images:</t>

<ul>
<li>An MTA must verify BIMI, and if it passes, add additional headers containing the logo
to be displayed.</li>
</ul>
<t>The MUA must check to see if a message passed BIMI before loading the BIMI image.</t>
<t>While the MTA MAY stamp BIMI-related information in the message headers, they should not
be relied upon by an MUA without additional checks to make sure they were added by a
trusted source, for example, making sure the MTA strips existing headers on ingress, or
by checking for a bimi pass in a trusted Authentication-Results header.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="leveraging-arc-for-mta-mua-communication"><name>Leveraging ARC for MTA MUA communication</name>
<t>If both the MTA and MUA support ARC then this MAY be used by the MUA to check that the
BIMI evaluation was undertaken by a trusted MTA. In this case the MTA MUST add bimi
entries to the Authentication-Results and ARC-Authentication-Results headers.
The MUA MUST evaluate ARC, and only use ARC sets which have passed and were added by
known good servers. This evaluation MUST stop at the first ARC fail.</t>
<t>If the MUA is configured to require an evidence document then it MAY check for a policy.authority=pass
in the bimi Authentication-Results and decline to show a logo if that is not present.</t>
<t>If the MTA has added a BIMI-Indicator header containing the encoded SVG then the MTA
SHOULD also add a short hashed checksum of this SVG into the Authentication-Results set.
The MUA MUST disregard any BIMI-Indicator headers which do not have a matching hash in
the Authentication-Results headers.
The hashed checksum for the Indicator MAY be added in the policy.indicator-hash entry.
If no BIMI-Indicator is present, or if the hash does not match then the MUA MAY retrieve
the indicator from the evidence document at URL specified in the policy.authority-uri if
present, from the SVG at the URL specified in the policy.indicator-uri if present and if
the MUA does not require a verified evidence document, or by evaluating BIMI directly
using the domain and selector from the bimi Authentication-Results entry.
The BIMI-Location header is not protected from forgery in the ARC set, and MUST NOT be used.</t>
<t>NOTE: This needs to be added to draft-brand-indicators-for-message-identification and relevant
entries registered with IANA  A hashed Indicator will need to be added to the AR set
policy.indicator-uri to be added to draft</t>
</section>

<section anchor="image-retrieval"><name>Image Retrieval</name>
<t>A core part of the BIMI specification is that the MUA will retrieve an image file to
display for each BIMI-validated message. There are multiple ways to accomplish this,
for example:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>In its most basic setup, a BIMI-capable MUA could retrieve the image file directly
from the site specified in the BIMI-Location header.</t>
</li>
<li><t>A BIMI capable MTA will add a header containing the Base64 encoded SVG of the image file.
The MUA can use this header to retrieve the already validated image file for display. This
is the recommended method of image retrieval as the work of retrieval and validation has
already been done by the MTA.  A consideration for this method may be the additional
storage requirements for adding a base64-encoded version of the SVG, where the original
file could be between 1 and 30 kilobytes, and encoding may add 35% to that size.</t>
</li>
<li><t>Other providers may choose to cache the associated images in a local store which could
be used as the BIMI resource address in the headers of a BIMI-approved message in a
sort of proxy configuration.</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="limited-use-of-http-redirects"><name>Limited use of HTTP Redirects</name>

<ul>
<li><t>Receivers may choose not to follow HTTP redirects when retrieving images or evidence
documents, or may choose to follow only a limited number of redirects.</t>
</li>
<li><t>When setting up BIMI, senders should eliminate, or limit the use of HTTP redirects to
avoid images being unretrievable by receivers who either do not support the use of
HTTP redirection, or have limited its use.</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="ttl-of-cached-images"><name>TTL of cached images</name>
<t>In some circumstances it is necessary to cache the images that an MUA would want to load.
For example, if a domain owner has a short TTL time, it would force the MUA to look it up
in an unreasonably short period of time. In this case, a receiver may want to set its
own TTL.</t>
<t>One option is to set it to several hours, or a day; another option is to set the TTL to
the same as the expiration period in the evidence document that contains the BIMI image. The
downside is that the caching mechanism might need to check for certificate revocation, and
then re-fetch images.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="mua-authors-1"><name>MUA Authors</name>

<section anchor="image-display"><name>Image Display</name>
<t>Although BIMI does not define an aspect ratio for Brand Indicators it is expected that the
majority of receivers will display them in a square or circular space. Is it recommended
to brands that their Indicators should be constructed to display in a 1:1 aspect ratio, receivers
should design the user interface display for BIMI Indicators with this in mind.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="security-concerns"><name>Security Concerns</name>
<t>Receivers should consider the impact of XML bomb or &quot;billion laughs&quot; Denial of Service attacks when
handling XML documents such as when validating SVG documents.
<eref target="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2003-1564">CVE-2003-1564</eref> is an example of this attack.</t>
<t>When validating XML documents, receivers should consider the security and privacy implications of
retrieving external entries referenced in those documents.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="privacy-concerns"><name>Privacy Concerns</name>
<t>There is some concern that the retrieval of the iconography could result in a privacy leak.<br />
As the images are retrieved, it's possible that the image provider could track the retrieving
system in some way. This has implications whether it be the sender or provider that is hosting
the image. For example, a sender could include a singular selector for a single recipient, or
a provider could append a tracking string to the image URI in the header.</t>
<t>A receiver may choose to track the number of selectors an organizational domain is permitted to
use and deny processing if this exceeds a defined limit. Similarly, a receiver may choose to
track and limit distinct Indicator URLs.</t>
<t>MTAs are encouraged to cache BIMI Records, evidence documents, and Indicators to limit tracking.</t>
<t>MUAs are encouraged to extract Indicators from the BIMI-Indicator header rather than retrieving
them directly from the source, as doing so will limit any data exposure to the MTA processing
the message. The BIMI approved SVG profile prohibits an SVG from loading external elements,
this removes the risk of tracking when an Indicator is shown in the client.</t>
<t>An in-depth discussion of all the potential privacy leaks with respect to loading or embedding
images is outside the scope of this document.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="brands-1"><name>Brands</name>

<section anchor="logo-hosting-considerations"><name>Logo Hosting Considerations</name>
<t>The logo you wish to associate with your brand can be hosted anywhere, not necessarily within the
domain that will be used to send the messages.  Doing so may make it easier to associate during
inspection, though it is understood that not all entities have a web server at the domain associated
with their email messages.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="cdn-considerations"><name>CDN Considerations</name>
<t>If the logo is behind a CDN (Content Delivery Network) this may prevent automated systems from
reaching the resource.  The automated systems may not appear to be a proper browser experience,
and would not be able to correctly respond to a challenge that the CDN may use to protect a
site, and therefore unable to retrieve the logo file.  If possible, those BIMI logos/resources
should be marked as unprotected, allowing any who request the resource to do so without possibility
of a challenge.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="domains-listed-in-your-evidence-document"><name>Domains listed in your evidence document</name>
<t>While obtaining an evidence document, an entity is expected to provide
at least one domain name.  There exists the opportunity to list additional
domains in the &quot;SAN&quot; field of the certificate.  These domains may or may
not match the 5322.From domain, but must match the domain being used in
the BIMI assertion record.  When using the organizational domain, other
third-level domains can take advantage of the evidence document as well.<br />
Within the core specification, it is discussed how the evaluator should
look at the original domain being used, as well as the Organizational
Domain.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="logo-designers"><name>Logo Designers</name>

<section anchor="known-issues"><name>Known Issues</name>
</section>

<section anchor="adherence-to-svg-p-s"><name>Adherence to SVG P/S</name>
<t>There may be a few issues that designers may experience when trying to adhere to SVG P/S.</t>

<ul>
<li>SVG P/S is based on SVG Tiny 1.2, which does not allow for certain types of gradients.  When trying
to convert/save as SVG Tiny 1.2, it will typically result in an embedded raster file. This is not
compliant with SVG P/S, and could result in display issues.</li>
<li>When exporting to SVG Tiny 1.2 with Adobe Illustrator, the application will insert <tt>x</tt> and <tt>y</tt>
attributes within the <tt>svg</tt> element.  These need to be removed to comply with SVG P/S.</li>
</ul>
</section>

<section anchor="tools"><name>Tools</name>
</section>

<section anchor="caveats"><name>Caveats</name>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="basic-flow-example"><name>Basic flow example</name>
<t>One sample implementation of BIMI by a receiver, who does everything on-the-fly, is as following:</t>

<ul>
<li><t>Upon receipt of a message, the receiver checks to see if the message passes aligned-SPF
or DKIM, and DMARC, and ensures that the sending domain has a DMARC policy of <tt>quarantine</tt>
or <tt>reject</tt> per local receiver policy, while properly applying the appropriate DMARC
policy to the message.</t>
</li>
<li><t>If the message passes prior checks, the receiver will then check to see if the domain
in the From: address has a BIMI record (or, if the message has a BIMI-Selector header that
is covered by the DKIM-Signature, uses that to do the BIMI query in DNS).</t>
</li>
<li><t>If a BIMI record is found, the receiver checks for the lps tag. If present and true then the
receiver normalizes the local-part of the sending address and checks for a BIMI
record using the normalized selector. If a BIMI record is found this is used in place of the
BIMI record containing the lps tag.</t>
</li>
<li><t>If a BIMI record is found, the receiver then retrieves the VMC from the location
that the BIMI record points to, and attempts to verify the VMC using a trusted root
certificate.</t>
</li>
<li><t>Upon successful verification of the VMC, the receiver extracts the verified image from
the VMC. If the SVG also passes the SVG validation steps then this is a successful BIMI verification.</t>
</li>
<li><t>If the BIMI verification fails then the MTA must not indicate to the MUA to show
a BIMI image. The MUA MAY show a default image such as a set of initials, or unidentified sender.</t>
</li>
<li><t>The email receiver then does the rest of its anti-spam, anti-malware, and anti-phishing checks as
discussed in <eref target="#message-classification">Message Classification</eref> below.</t>
</li>
<li><t>The email receiver then adds the relevant Authentication-Results and BIMI-* headers to the message
to signal to the downstream email client that the message passed BIMI and that is safe to load the
logo.</t>
</li>
<li><t>Eventually, the MUA checks the BIMI-* headers, decodes the image in the BIMI-Indicator header,
and displays it as the sender photo (or however else it chooses to render the BIMI logo in conjunction
with the message).</t>
</li>
</ul>

<section anchor="message-classification"><name>Message Classification</name>
<t>The successful validation of BIMI does NOT indicate that a message is not spam, malware, or phishing.</t>
<t>It is expected that receivers undertake their usual message filtering and classification steps, and
take the results of these checks into consideration when deciding if a BIMI Indicator should be
shown to the user.</t>
<t>If classification is performed before BIMI is evaluated then a receiver MAY CHOOSE to skip BIMI
processing for that message, in this case they SHOULD add a bimi=skipped entry to the Authentication-Results
header for that message, and SHOULD add a comment stating the reasons for skipping BIMI processing.</t>
<t>If a message is classified as phishing or malware then the MUA SHOULD NOT display the logo.</t>
<t>If a message is classified as spam (meaning that the message comes from a known
brand, but contains spammy content), then the email receiver MAY choose not to display the
logo.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="domain-reputation"><name>Domain Reputation</name>
<t>Receivers are advised to consider incorporating local sources of domain trust intelligence
into the processes which ultimately determine whether or not BIMI logos are displayed.
Simply because a sending domain passes BIMI requirements does not mean the images should
automatically be displayed in the MUA; a site may impose further restrictions based on
domain reputation.</t>
<t>One source of additional reputation intelligence could be a platform that the email provider
has created to calculate domain trust based on historical traffic; another is an explicit list of
trusted domains that has been curated by an individual provider; a third is a list that is purchased
from a vendor that might be a pass/fail or a scored list; another option is some mix of any of the
previous three.</t>

<section anchor="rolling-up-based-upon-domain-vs-organizational-domain"><name>Rolling up based upon domain vs organizational domain</name>
<t>BIMI is designed to be able to work on selectors, and so in theory a brand/domain could specify
multiple BIMI logos and differentiate them on a per-domain (per-selector) basis. The advantage
for the brand is that they can choose the image they want the user to see depending upon various
conditions (e.g., seasonal images, regional images, etc.).</t>
<t>However, for an email receiver, it may be easier to roll up BIMI logos on an organizational domain
basis. One reason may be for the purposes of reputation, another may be for simplifying management
of images. In this case, it would need to be made clear to brands that this is how the loading of
BIMI images works. This documentation could live on a postmaster site, under technical documentation,
or other official page maintained by the receiver. It could then be referred to when sending
organizations ask about how to on-board to BIMI at the receiver, and provide official guidance about
the way it works at the site.</t>
<t>If rolling up by organizational domain, then it may make sense to use a &quot;lowest common denominator&quot;
approach. That is, an organizational domain must meet all the requirements for BIMI, rather than only
a sub-domain. The reason for this is that if sub.brand.com gets an image due to having strong authentication
policies, but brand.com does not, then this may cause confusion because a user may learn to associate
sub.brand.com and its image with brand.com; and if brand.com can be spoofed even though sub.brand.com cannot,
that can lead to users becoming more susceptible to phishing from brand.com.</t>
<t>To alleviate this, receivers may wish to show logos only for domains that have organizational domains with
strong DMARC policies. Or, if an organizational domain does not have a strong DMARC policy but a sub-domain
does, then it may treat the organizational domain as if it does have a strong DMARC policy so as to prevent
a phisher or spammer from impersonating the brand or any of its sub-domains.</t>
<t>A strong DMARC policy may be defined as one which has some level of enforcement. For example, a
p=quarantine policy with an effective pct=100, or a p=reject policy.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="vmc-root-of-trust"><name>VMC Root of Trust</name>
<t>VMCs are verified back to their issuing Mark Verifying Authority (MVA). Receivers may wish to maintain their
own list of trusted CAs for BIMI rather than relying on a generally available bundle of trusted Root
Certificates such as those distributed with browsers or operating systems. The AuthIndicators Working Group
will maintain a list of known VMC Root CA Certificates to help bootstrap such a list.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="security-concerns-relating-to-message-authentication"><name>Security Concerns Relating to Message Authentication</name>
<t>BIMI relies upon the foundations of existing messsage authentication
mechanisms. As of the writing of this document, those are DMARC, SPF, and
DKIM. Each of these were created several years ago, and with time, some issues
have been found, most specifically with SPF and DKIM. The items below are not
specific to BIMI, and the referenced documents have more information.</t>

<section anchor="spf-concerns"><name>SPF Concerns</name>
<t>SPF <xref target="RFC7208"></xref> is used to denote from where a message should be arriving,
typically based on IP.  SPF will only provide authentication for the first
hop when sending from the originator to another internet mail site.  There
are some mechanisms within the SPF that could be misused in a number of
ways:</t>

<ul>
<li>SPF allows for a +all mechanism.  This effectively allows all hosts on the
internet to be authenticated as this domain</li>
<li>Some domains publish domains with includes that result in a large
number of IPs that can be used by any number of other senders</li>
<li>A sender could typo a CIDR from an ip4/ip6 statement</li>
<li>A platform may not properly validate users are attached to a specified
domain when sending</li>
<li>A platform may allow for some loose rules relating to forwards, which
could permit an attacker to misuse a domain</li>
</ul>
<t>It's suggested that a receiver should be extremely careful when allowing a
message to be authenticated solely on SPF.  Similarly, a sender should do
as much as they can to utilize both SPF and DKIM, properly aligned.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="dkim-concerns"><name>DKIM Concerns</name>
<t>DKIM <xref target="RFC6376"></xref> is a cryptographic signature meant to protect against
tampering with a message. This method is the most likely to survive forwarding
to another internet site.</t>

<ul>
<li>DKIM Replay is a method by which an attacker attempts to subvert a previously
sent message, and use the signature to send something different.
See [draft-chuang-dkim-replay-problem] for additional information.</li>
<li>Poor selection for signature algorithm, the key length, or the length
which a key has been in use</li>
<li>Oversigning of headers (RFC6376, Section 8.15) is considered a partial
protection against DKIM Replay, and should be considered by senders
implementing BIMI</li>
<li>Expiration of signatures utilizing the <tt>-x</tt> option while signing</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="bimi-playbook-checklist"><name>BIMI Playbook Checklist</name>
<t>There are several factors to consider for email receivers on things that can go wrong; below are
a handful of considerations:</t>

<ul>
<li>Failing to verify a VMC</li>
<li>Failing to extract an Indicator from a validated VMC</li>
<li>Failing to validate a SVG against the recommended profile</li>
<li>Failing to parse a gzipped SVG Indicator</li>
<li>Failing to load a logo in the email client</li>
<li>Failing to access the logo (e.g., permissions errors)</li>
<li>Connectivity problems to the logo</li>
<li>Failing to display a correct logo in the email client</li>
<li>Having the wrong logo stored for a brand (i.e., uploading it to a local store but associating
it with the wrong brand)</li>
<li>Caching a logo for too long after it has updated</li>
</ul>
<t>There are many reasons why a logo may fail to load; having tools to investigate (logs, headers
in messages, internal documentation that is clearly written, having the knowledge pushed out
to multiple escalation channels) is important for investigation.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="public-documentation"><name>Public documentation</name>

<section anchor="documentation-for-brands"><name>Documentation For Brands:</name>
<t>It is ideal to publish the criteria that is used by your site to determine when BIMI will
be displayed. It is fine to say that you use some internal domain reputation metrics as
additional criteria to determine whether or not a logo should be displayed, and it isn't
necessary to give away the exact nature of the algorithm other than to say &quot;You must maintain
good sending practices.&quot;</t>
<t>If you use an explicit allow list, a site may want to list the minimum requirements, and the
method of applying to be listed.  Similarly, a provider may wish to state what type of
activity will revoke the decision to display logos previously approved.</t>
</section>

<section anchor="documentation-for-users"><name>Documentation For Users:</name>
<t>BIMI is not meant to instill additional trust in messages, and it is important to make
this known to your users. All messages, even those with logos, should still be treated with
(mild) skepticism, and any action regarding the message should still be individually evaluated.
It's possible for a site that has a high trust value to become compromised and send fraudulent
messages that could compromise a user's system. Ensure your customers have a place that documents
BIMI and demonstrates how to check messages for fraud.</t>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="appendix"><name>Appendix</name>

<section anchor="glossary"><name>Glossary</name>

<ul>
<li><t>MUA - Mail User Agent - The application used to read messages by the end user.  This could
be a thick client or a web-based application.</t>
</li>
<li><t>MTA - Mail Transfer Agent - Software used to transfer messages between two systems, typically
between two sites, using SMTP as the protocol.</t>
</li>
<li><t>MBP - Mailbox Provider - An organization who provides access to a user's mailbox via
some method such as IMAP/POP/MAPI/Webmail.</t>
</li>
<li><t>SPF - <eref target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7208">Sender Policy Framework</eref> -
SPF is a framework that designates which systems should be sending for a given
domain.  This can be a list of IPs, CIDRs, or references to DNS records.  As the sender
should be controlling their DNS, they should understand which IPs should be sending as
their domain.</t>
</li>
<li><t>DKIM - <eref target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6376">DomainKeys Identified Mail</eref> -
DKIM is a system by which a chosen set of headers, combined with the message
contents, are cryptographically signed, and then validated by the receiving system.
Using DNS, the receiving system can retrieve a public key, and then validate the signature
within the headers of a message. When implemented properly, the systems responsible for
sending the messages for a given domain name should be the only ones capable
of creating messages that correctly validates.</t>
</li>
<li><t>DMARC - <eref target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7489">Domain-based Message Authentication, Reporting, and Conformance</eref> -
DMARC is a message authentication mechanism that works with SPF and DKIM. The
BIMI specification requires that a message passes DMARC. In order for a message to pass
DMARC, one of SPF or DKIM must successfully validate, and the domain in the From: address
must align with the domain that passed SPF or DKIM.</t>
</li>
<li><t>Alignment - Alignment refers to the organizational domain, as defined by DMARC, of the
domain in the From: address being the same as the organizational domain that passed SPF or
DKIM. For example, baz.example.com has an organizational domain of example.com;
bar.foo.example.com also has an organizational domain of example.com. It aligns with
org.example.com, because both have the same organizational domain. A definition of
organizational domain and methods of discovery may be found in the <eref target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc7489">DMARC</eref> RFC.</t>
</li>
<li><t>MVA - Mark Verifying Authority - An entity that a receiver uses to certify that the
iconography that they intend to use with BIMI is properly/legally licensed for their use.</t>
</li>
<li><t>DRA - Dispute Resolution Authority - This organization will moderate between two entities
that believe they are both entitled to use a logo.  Receivers should then abide by the
decision of the DRA as it pertains to logo usage in the MUA.</t>
</li>
<li><t>VMC - Verified Mark Certificate - An Extended Validation Certificate is used in conjunction with BIMI to
create a place where information pertaining to iconography for a sending domain can be
securely verified. In the case of BIMI, hashes for an MVA-approved set of iconography
will be stored in a field within the certificate. This should allow a receiver site to
validate the retrieved imagery before putting the BIMI image URI into the message headers.</t>
</li>
<li><t>Local-part - The locally interpret string part of an email address which appears before the
at-sign character (&quot;@&quot;, ASCII value 64) which is then followed by an Internet
domain.</t>
</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>

<section anchor="contributors"><name>Contributors</name>
<t>TBD</t>
</section>

<section anchor="references"><name>References</name>
<t>The full BIMI verification spec can be found at:
  <eref target="https://github.com/authindicators/rfc-brand-indicators-for-message-identification">https://github.com/authindicators/rfc-brand-indicators-for-message-identification</eref></t>
<t>Verified Mark Certificates Usage:</t>
<t><eref target="http://bimigroup.org/resources/VMC_Guidelines_latest.pdf">http://bimigroup.org/resources/VMC_Guidelines_latest.pdf</eref></t>
</section>

</middle>

<back>
<references><name>Normative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
</references>
<references><name>Informative References</name>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6376.xml"/>
<xi:include href="https://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7208.xml"/>
</references>

</back>

</rfc>
